- [Ryan] Hi, my name is Ryan Jones.
I'm a senior project manager at TPGi,
and I'm also a JAWS user.
Today I'm going to show
you a brief example
of using JAWS on a webpage.
We'll show a good example of a webpage
that has accessibility built into it.
And then an example of what happens
when you're on a webpage
that does not have accessibility.
These samples are made by the W3C
who also makes the web standards.
So I have Google Chrome
open and JAWS running,
and I'm just going to start down arrowing
through part of this particular webpage.
And we'll hear what JAWS says.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Heading
level two navigation menu,
list of four items.
- [Ryan] So JAWS told me I
just moved past a heading.
And then it says I'm moving into a list
with four items in it.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Link Home.
- [Ryan] Link home, which
means this is a link
that I could activate,
and the name of the link is "home".
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Link News.
- [Ryan] A link called "news".
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Visited link tickets.
- [Ryan] A link called "tickets"
that I have visited before.
So it says "visited link".
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Survey.
- [Ryan] The word "survey",
which is not a link, it's just text.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] List end.
- [Ryan] And then I'm
at the end of the list.
If I keep down arrowing.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Heading
level one Citylights Survey.
- [Ryan] I get to a new heading
called "Citylights Survey".
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Heading level two,
This Week's Survey: More city
parks - a pain or a gain?
- [Ryan] So if I continue to arrow down,
I'll move through the survey,
but I'm going to jump forward
and find the edit boxes
where I know there are some information
that I will need to type in.
So I'm going to press a JAWS
shortcut key to let me do that.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Name.
Edit has popup menu.
- [Ryan] And JAWS said "name",
and it says that it's an edit box
so that I know that I could
type something in here,
if I needed to.
If I continue to move forward
through these fields...
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Email address.
Edit has popup menu.
- [Ryan] There's one for email address.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Retype email.
Edit has popup menu.
- [Ryan] I need to retype the email.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Submit button.
- [Ryan] The submit button.
There's another way that
I could bring up a list
of all of the form fields on this page,
assuming that they are labeled properly.
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Select a Form Field dialog.
List one, list view.
Submit button 15 of 15.
- [Ryan] And I'm at
the bottom of the page.
So if I scroll up the list,
I'll find all the form fields there.
The names will make sense
because this page does have
accessibility built into it.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Escape.
- [Ryan] Now I'm going to switch
over to this similar page,
same page,
but it's going to not have
accessibility built into it.
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Welcome to Citylights.
Inaccessible survey.
- [Ryan] So this is the
inaccessible version.
If I'm back on that same
navigation menu on this page
where there's things that
are not done properly,
let's hear what JAWS says.
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Unlabeled graphic graphic IMG
slash nav Home on mouse over.
- [Ryan] So this was the
thing on the other page
that said home link.
Now it's giving me a bunch of gibberish.
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Unlabeled graphic graphic
IMG slash nav News on mouse over.
- [Ryan] So these are images here
in this navigation menu
that are not properly labeled,
so JAWS doesn't know what to call them.
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Unlabeled graphic graphic
IMG slash nav Facts on mouse over.
- [Ryan] And I'm just
pressing the down arrow key.
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Unlabeled graphic graphic
IMG slash nav Survey on mouse over.
Citylights Survey.
This Week's Survey: More city-
- [Ryan] JAWS did not tell me
that there were headings here
because this text was not
marked up with the heading text.
In a similar example,
if I bring up the same list of form fields
that I used on the previous page...
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Select a form field dialog.
List one, list view.
Unlabeled one combo box, quick menu,
one of 14.
- [Ryan] Instead of the nice
properly labeled form fields
that I had on the other page...
- [JAWS Screen Reader]
Radio button not checked.
- [Ryan] I'm not getting any labels
on these particular form fields,
because they were not properly labeled
for accessibility.
- [JAWS Screen Reader] Escape.
- [Ryan] As the screen reader user,
I can use all kinds of
different shortcut keys
to move around this page,
move to different form fields,
links, buttons, headings.
All of those things that
I can move to, though,
have to have been coded
properly for accessibility,
in order for the shortcut keys to work,
and in order for JAWS
to read the information.